Jupiter is the largest and
oldest planet in our solar
system. Its history spans 4.5
billion years. This gas giant is
made of the same elements as a
star, but it did not grow
massive enough to ignite.
Jupiter’s appearance is the
result of its swirling interior
of gases and liquids – producing
a tapestry of colorful cloud
bands as well as the iconic
Great Red Spot.
The Great Red Spot is a gigantic
storm. It’s an anticyclone,
and with no land mass on the
planet to slow it down,
the Great Red Spot has
raged for over a century.
But scientists studying the spot
have noticed that it has been
changing over time. The color is
deepening, and it’s actually
shrinking and getting rounder.
Those studying it expected to
therefore see the wind speeds
inside the Great Red Spot
increasing as the storm shrinks
– like an ice skater who spins
faster as she pulls in her arms.
But this isn’t the case.
Data reveals the storm isn’t
spinning faster, it’s actually
getting taller. You can think of
it like working with pottery.
As the wide lump of clay spins,
forces within are driving it
taller.  So from our
perspective, looking down on the
clouds, we see the spot
getting smaller and rounder.
The Great Red Spot used to be
big enough to fit three Earths.
Now, it’s just a little over
one.
These discoveries were made by
analyzing data from numerous
NASA missions, including
Voyager, Hubble, and most
recently, Juno.
And through more
investigations, scientists hope
to unlock more secrets of the
mysterious Great Red Spot.
[beeping]